{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Court painter Daniel Maclise depicted this monarch meeting a noblewoman At Hampton Court in one painting. This monarch appears on the bottom left approaching the royal party of Francis I in the landscape painting Field of the Cloth of Gold. This man employed foreigner Hans Holbein the Younger, who depicted this king in a portrait situated next to one of Jane Seymour and this man's father Henry VII [[the Seventh]]. For ten points, name this English king who is depicted in several portraits with his six wives.",
      "answer": "Henry VIII ]"
    },
    {
      "question": "Secretary of War Jefferson Davis sent this man to Europe to study the tactics of the Crimean War, and later in his life, he would serve as governor of New Jersey. In letters to his wife, this general describes himself as \"the power of the land\" and the commander in chief as a \"well meaning baboon.\" This general was removed from command following the Battle of Antietam, and would challenge President Lincoln in the Election of 1864. For ten points, name this prideful Union general, known for his cautiousness in battle.",
      "answer": "George B. McClellan"
    },
    {
      "question": "A member of this family wrote the book On the Art of the Cinema and ordered the kidnapping of film director Shin Sang-ok. Members of this family promote the ideology of \"military first\" or \"Songun\" and a quasi-religion called \"Juche\" [[JOO-cheh]]. A member of this family met with Dennis Rodman in 2013 and was rumored to be transferring power to his sister Yo-jong due to health issues in 2020. Dictators Il-sung, Jong-il, and Jong-un belong to, for ten points, what family that controls North Korea?",
      "answer": "Kim family"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a failed attempt to prevent this event, a route along Appel Quay was decided upon by Oskar Potiorek. A false turn by Leopold Lojka [[LOY-kuh]] resulted in this event, which was preceded by a failed attack with a hand grenade. An FN Model 1910 was used to carry out this attack, which also resulted in the death of its central target’s wife, Sophie. The Black Hand helped organize this event, which was perpetrated by the Bosnian Serb Gavrilo Princip. For ten points, name this 1914 attack that killed the heir presumptive of Austria-Hungary.",
      "answer": "Assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the 1970s, this man was nominated for Best Recording for Children at the Grammys for an educational album featuring [this man] and His Gang vs. Mr. Tooth Decay. Jimmy Carter tasked this athlete with a 1980 tour of Africa to endorse the boycott of the Moscow Olympics. In an effort to legitimize his regime, dictator Mobutu Sese Seko hosted a contest between this athlete and George Foreman, the so-called \"Rumble in the Jungle.\" Cassius Clay was once the name of, for ten points, which boxer, known as \"The Greatest\"?",
      "answer": [
        "Muhammad Ali",
        "Cassius Marcellus Clay Jr. before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Moro of Mindanao declared one of these specific conflicts after the government of Ferdinand Marcos killed many of its acolytes in the Corregidor massacre. During one of these specific conflicts, scholar Usman dan Fodio united many of the Hausa independent states after being appointed \"Commander of the Faithful.\" Ottoman sultan Mehmed V formally declared a \"Great\" one of these religious wars against the Allies during World War One. For ten points, name these Islamic holy wars, often considered a counterpart to a Christian \"Crusade.\"",
      "answer": "Jihad"
    },
    {
      "question": "Civil War general Benjamin Butler was given the nickname “Spoons” for taking silverware from a woman during the Union’s occupation of this city, the most populous in the Confederacy. In another conflict, Edward Pakenham was defeated in this city by a force assisted by pirate Jean Lafitte [[lah-FEET]] in a battle fought after the signing of the Treaty of Ghent. Andrew Jackson won the Battle of, for ten points, what city major port city annexed into the Union by the Louisiana Purchase?",
      "answer": "New Orleans"
    },
    {
      "question": "This prime minister ordered British forces to bombard Alexandria in response to the 'Urabi [[oo-RAH-bee]] revolt. The Hawarden [[HAR-den]] Kite was an infamous news scoop that suggested this man supported Irish Home Rule. This leader attacked a prominent political rival over their response to the “Bulgarian Horrors” in his Midlothian campaign. For ten points, name this four-time Liberal British prime minister during the nineteenth century and rival of Benjamin Disraeli.",
      "answer": "William Ewart Gladstone"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this war, one participant revoked their ambassador in Sweden for openly harboring deserters. Mark Satin wrote a \"Manual\" which taught men how to integrate into Canadian society during this war, and Arlo Guthrie recounts traveling to Whitehall Street in New York and intentionally acting mentally ill in the protest song \"Alice's Restaurant Massacree.\" Men like Bill Clinton and Dick Cheney faced accusations of dodging, for ten points, what 1960s and 1970s conflict in Southeast Asia?",
      "answer": [
        "Vietnam War",
        "Second Indochina War"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure incorporated a band he managed, Lou Reed's Velvet Underground, into his multimedia art show, the Exploding Plastic Inevitable. This man was shot after the author of the radical feminist work, the SCUM Manifesto, Valerie Solanas, claimed he had too much control over her life. Silkscreen ink was used by this artist to depict the preeminent Communist leader Mao Zedong. 32 Campbell's Soup Cans and the Marilyn Diptych were created by, for ten points, which American Pop artist?",
      "answer": "Andy Warhol or Andrew Warhola, Jr."
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An impending munitions delivery from the SS Ypiranga [[ee-pee-RAHN-gah]] led to an attack in this city, which was then under a six-month occupation by one country following the Tampico Affair, which in turn led to the downfall of Victoriano Huerta. Half a century earlier, this city was the subject of the first amphibious assault in U.S. military history. Winfield Scott led an invasion of central Mexico through, for ten points, what Mexican port city?",
        "answer": "Veracruz"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man participated in the Siege of Veracruz after having his ship, the USS Mississippi repaired due to damage during the capture of Tampico. This man later led warships against Japan, leading to the Convention of Kanagawa.",
        "answer": [
          "Matthew C. Perry or Matthew Calbraith Perry",
          "Commodore Perry"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Architect William Thornton convinced one side during this event to spare the Patent Office, which briefly hosted Congress following this event. Partially motivated by the American invasion of Upper Canada, Robert Ross's victory at the Battle of Bladensburg led to this violent incursion. Dolley Madison saved a portrait of George Washington during, for ten points, what destructive event during the War of 1812 that followed the capture of the U.S. national capital?",
        "answer": [
          "Burning of Washington",
          "Burning of D.C.",
          "equivalents to \"burning\" like \"destruction\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Burning of Washington destroyed the first iteration of the Library of Congress, resulting in which former president donating and selling many works from his private collection?",
        "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The explosion of a water tank in Mayak led to a nuclear disaster in the southern portion of this range, irradiating nearby Lake Karachay. A city nestled in this range named Magnitogorsk became an industrial hub in the 1930s due to a mountain there being made up of fifty-five percent iron ore. The Council for Evacuation, or GKO, moved over 1500 factories beyond this mountain range in the midst of Operation Barbarossa. For ten points, name this mountain range that historically divided the European and Asian portions of Russia.",
        "answer": [
          "Ural Mountains or Urals",
          "Uralskiye gory"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Uralic city of Yekaterinburg was the site of the execution of Tsar Nicholas II and his entire family, including which daughter of his who was rumored to have escaped, leading to imposters like Anna Anderson claiming to be her?",
        "answer": "Anastasia Romanov or Grand Duchess Anastasia Nikolaevna of Russia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This character is enticed by a sign to \"Join the Army and See the World\" and dies in the jungles of Vietnam in an underground protest film by Whitney Lee Savage. Margaret Thatcher labelled the European Parliament with this fictional character's name due to its perceived ineffectiveness. Despite making a short appearance in Plane Crazy, this character and his paramour first appeared in the short film Steamboat Willie. Walt Disney originally voiced, for ten points, which mascot of the Disney corporation?",
        "answer": "Mickey Mouse"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fredo claims he betrayed his brother due to being sent to run a \"Mickey Mouse nightclub\" in which gangster drama film revolving around the actions of the Corleone family?",
        "answer": "The Godfather"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man commanded a fleet that seized a treasure worth over thirty million present- day pounds from the São Filipe [[SOW fil-EEP-ee]]. This man commanded a raid that tried to land at El Puntal [[EHL [[PUHN-tahl]] while destroying dozens of Spanish capital ships in the Bay of Cádiz, known as the \"singeing [[SINJ-ing]] of the King of Spain's beard.\" Earlier, this man commanded the flagship Golden Hind and claimed \"New Albion\" in California. For ten points, name this British privateer who led a 1577 to 1580 circumnavigation of the world.",
        "answer": "Francis Drake"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Drake died while raiding Portobelo in what modern-day country, where the bulk of Scotland's disastrous Darién colony was later located?",
        "answer": [
          "Panama or Republic of Panama",
          "or República de Panamá"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this modern-day country, a breakaway general who was fond of using a metaphor about plucking the tail off a horse held off Metellus Pius and Pompey for seven years. This present-day country was the location of Quintus Sertorius's attempt to rebel against Rome. Hannibal's attack on Saguntum in this present-day country began the Second Punic War. Hadrian and Trajan were both born in what is now this country. For ten points, name this country where Romans expanded cities such as Valentia, Corduba, and Toletum, or modern Toledo.",
        "answer": [
          "Spain",
          "Kingdom of Spain",
          "or Reino de Espana",
          "Roman Hispania"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the division of Hispania Ulterior in 27 BC, the southwestern portion of Iberia comprised which province, the name of which was historically an alternate for Portugal?",
        "answer": "Hispana Lusitania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Despite playing for the Browns, Joe Gedeon earned a lifetime ban for knowledge of this event. Former federal judge Kenesaw Mountain Landis ignored an acquittal of eight men during a faulty trial concerning this event and banned the defendants from one sport. Despite having a .375 batting average and committing zero errors, \"Shoeless Joe\" Jackson was banned for his alleged involvement in this event. Owner Charles Comiskey's poor wages led to, for ten points, which baseball scandal where a team threw the 1919 World Series in exchange for money?",
        "answer": [
          "Black Sox Scandal",
          "descriptions which include the White Sox throwing the World Series"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Earlier, Kennesaw Mountain Landis struck down a civil suit brought by the newly created \"Federal League\" against the MLB, which the Federal League brought to court using which 19th century antitrust act?",
        "answer": "1890 Sherman Anti-trust Act"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A school of historiographical thought named for Columbia professor William Archibald Dunning was accused of taking \"white supremacist\" stances on this time period, leading to a direct refutation by W.E.B. Du Bois [[doo-BOYSS]] in his book Black [this era]. In one thesis, historian Erich Foner disputes that \"carpetbaggers\" and \"scalawags\" were the cause of the failure of this period. The military occupation of the rebelling Confederate States occurred during, for ten points, which period in the South in the 19th century?",
        "answer": [
          "Reconstruction",
          "Black Reconstruction"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Dunning School demonized a branch of the Republican party, which took on this alliterative moniker, for botching Reconstruction by advocating for civil rights?",
        "answer": "Radical Republicans"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Gilded Age",
      "prompt": "Concerning late 19th century America, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Author of The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn who coined the term \"Gilded Age.\"",
          "answer": "Mark Twain or Samuel Langhorne Clemens"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scottish-born steel magnate and anti-unionist who promoted philanthropy in his \"Gospel of Wealth.\"",
          "answer": "Andrew Carnegie"
        },
        {
          "question": "Businessman who, alongside Henry Flagler, founded Standard Oil in 1870.",
          "answer": "John D. Rockefeller or John Davison Rockefeller Sr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Political machine of New York led by the infamous \"Boss\" Tweed which was known for its rampant corruption.",
          "answer": [
            "Tammany Hall or Tammany Society",
            "the Society of St. Tammany",
            "or Sons of St. Tammany",
            "Columbian Order"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Medieval term used to describe ruthlessly powerful businessmen like Cornelius Vanderbilt.",
          "answer": "Robber Baron"
        },
        {
          "question": "Third party named for an informal term for dollars which formed to oppose the growth of monopolies.",
          "answer": [
            "Greenback Party",
            "National Independent Party"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Disastrous 1887 act which aimed to subdivide Native reservations into western allotments of farmlands.",
          "answer": [
            "Dawes Act of 1887 or Dawes Severalty Act of 1887",
            "General Allotment Act"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Norwegian-American economist who was inspired to write The Theory of the Leisure Class in response to the excess of the Gilded Age.",
          "answer": "Thorstein Veblen or Thorstein Bunde Veblen"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Crisis of the Third Century",
      "prompt": "Concerning the chaotic third century AD, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Hegemonic empire which split into three distinct sections during the Crisis of the Third Century.",
          "answer": [
            "Roman Empire or Rome",
            "Imperium Rōmānum"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Popular religious group persecuted by Emperor Diocletian.",
          "answer": "Christians"
        },
        {
          "question": "Elite Roman guards who killed emperors such as Pupienus [[poo-pee-AY-nus]], Balbinus, and Maximus Thrax.",
          "answer": "Praetorian Guard or Cohortēs praetōriae"
        },
        {
          "question": "Silver currency of Rome which was debased during the early crisis and virtually abandoned by the reign of Gordian III.",
          "answer": [
            "Denarii",
            "Denarius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty of emperors whose members included Septimius and Caracalla, whose downfall coincided with the crisis.",
          "answer": "Severan Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "General and eventual emperor whose string of military victories led to the end of the crisis and his being crowned \"Restorer of the World.\"",
          "answer": "Aurelian or Lucius Domitius Aurelianus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dalmatian province of Rome that produced a series of emperors during the crisis, such as Decius and Probus.",
          "answer": [
            "Illyricum",
            "Roman Illyria"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term originally used for cities bound by treaty that referred to barbarian mercenaries whose influence grew during the crisis.",
          "answer": [
            "Foederati",
            "Foederatus"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Han Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Han Dynasty, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Large East Asian country whose primary ethnic group is named for the Han.",
          "answer": [
            "China",
            "Empire of China",
            "or Imperial China",
            "Zhōngguó",
            "People's Republic of China/a]",
            "PRC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Royal title created by Qin [[CHIN] Shi Huang, which the Han assumed in 202 BC.",
          "answer": "Emperor of China or Huángdì"
        },
        {
          "question": "Technology traditionally attributed to court official Cai Lun, who used pulp from the mulberry tree.",
          "answer": "Paper or Papermaking"
        },
        {
          "question": "Period which followed the collapse of the Han Dynasty, witnessing warfare between the states of Wei, Shu, and Wu.",
          "answer": "Three Kingdoms Period or Sānguó Shídài"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massive 184 AD peasant revolt named for the garment worn by its participants.",
          "answer": [
            "Yellow Turban Rebellion",
            "Yellow Scarves Rebellion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Confucian scholar and court official who briefly interrupted the Han with his own Xin [[SHIN]] Dynasty.",
          "answer": [
            "Wang Mang",
            "Jujun"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the Han dynasty who defeated the Chu at Gaixia [[\"GUY\"-SHAH]] to become sole ruler.",
          "answer": [
            "Liu Bang",
            "Emperor Gao",
            "or Gaozu of Han",
            "or Gaodi",
            "or Taizu"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Traditional name of Xi'an, which served as the capital of the Han dynasty.",
          "answer": "Chang'an"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man helped organize Illinois’ Populist Party and ran for U.S. Congress in 1895, losing to Hugh R. Belknap. After being charged for bribery, this man switched careers from being a civil lawyer to a criminal defense (20 pts)",
        "attorney. This man presided over a case where eleven Black men, including Ossian Sweet, killed a white man, as well as a case that the Chicago Tribune dubbed “The Trial (10 pts)",
        "of the Century.” For ten points, name this prominent criminal defense attorney who defended Leopold and Loeb [[LOBE]], as well as John Scopes, in the \"Monkey Trial.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Clarence Darrow or Clarence Seward Darrow"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The poet of Morgante, Luigi Pulci [[PUHL-chi]], wrote a verse poem celebrating this nobleman's victory in a 1469 jousting tournament. To acquire the support of this man, Sultan Qaitbay presented him with a (20 pts)",
        "giraffe which this man let roam the city streets, according to poet Antonio Costanzo. This politician survived an assassination attempt during the Pazzi Conspiracy, an act sanctioned by the sitting Pope and rival of his family (10 pts)",
        "Sixtus IV. For ten points, name this \"Magnificent\" ruler of Florence, the grandson of Cosimo."
      ],
      "answer": "Lorenzo de' Medici"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A passage in Pliny says that an important statue of this god had wool binding around the feet and was hollowed out and filled with oil that was removed only once per year. A fresco discovered at Pompeii shows this god wearing a white veil and carrying a (20 pts)",
        "sickle. This god, whom the Romans believes patronized an archaic Golden Age in Italy, was the namesake of a winter (10 pts)",
        "festival during which masters waited on slaves. For ten points, identify this father of Jupiter who the Romans worshipped at a cult center on the Capitoline hill."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Saturn",
        "Saturnalia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A person in this occupation nicknamed \"Madre Conchita\" likely masterminded the assassination of former president, Alvaro Obregon [[oh-breh-GOHN]] at Bombilla [[bohm-BEE-yah]] Cafe by José de León Toral. The constructed language lingua ignota was created by Hildegard (20 pts)",
        "von Bingen, who held this occupation in the County Palatine. Martin Luther first housed and later married a noble named (10 pts)",
        "Katharina who once was in this occupation. For ten points, name this monastic profession in the Catholic church held exclusively by women."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nuns",
        "Abbess",
        "or Sisters"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A Venetian convert led a subset of these states and built his namesake mosque to impress Lalla Lalla Oum, a princess of the Kabyle [[KAH-beel]]. Ships of this polity departing from Sale [[SAH-leh]] (20 pts)",
        "traveled across the Atlantic during a 17th century raid on Iceland in search of slaves. With assistance from Sweden and Sicily, the U.S. fought two namesake (10 pts)",
        "wars with people of these states, culminating in a blockade of Tripoli. For ten points, name these historical “pirate states” of the North African coast."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Barbary States",
        "Barbary Coast",
        "or Berber Coast"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2017, this state's officials brought in Irula tribesmen from the Indian subcontinent to capture invasive Burmese Pythons. Since the 1990s, a landfill in the south of this state has been piled over with soil to avoid odors, leading to the affectionate nickname \"Mount Trashmore.\" Lake (20 pts)",
        "Hell 'n Blazes is the source of this state's St. Johns River, which hosted the indigenous Timucua people as well as settlements of this state's namesake \"Crackers.\" (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this Southern state known in the 2010s for a namesake \"man\" who commits unusual crimes in places like the Everglades."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Florida",
        "Florida Man"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Composer Aaron Copland [[KOHP-land]] set a speech at one of these events in Alton to music, and the recently invented Pitman Shorthand allowed writers to keep up with the orators at these events. The ability of territories to exclude (20 pts)",
        "slavery through local legislation was espoused during these debates in the Freeport Doctrine. A Democrat and a future (10 pts)",
        "Republican president vied for a Senate seat in Illinois during, for ten points, which 1858 debates?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Lincoln-Douglas Debates Great Debates of 1858 before \"1858\" is read",
        "prompt on partial answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Before assuming his most notable position, this man was told \"May God curse your studies\" during a recruitment attempt by future ally William Farel. This theologian helped build the case of heresy against Michael (20 pts)",
        "Cervetus, who was then burned at the stake. This reformer pleaded with Francis I to stop persecuting the Huguenots in his native country in the preface to his magnum opus, (10 pts)",
        "Institutes of the Christian Religion. For ten points, name this French-Swiss reformer who expounded the doctrine of predestination while living in Geneva."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John Calvin or Jean Calvin",
        "Jean Cauvin"
      ]
    }
  ]
}